Guide to the Ronald R. Spadafora Papers 1911-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2010s) MS 3134
New-York Historical Society
- Education, circa 1993-2010s (Offsite-box 9797)
  Electrical Fire Cause Determination training manual, 1993 (with Spadafora completion certificate). Binder of fire science training material (labeled "fire marshal"). Spadafora binder of materials for Fire Science 303 course (Fire Investigations). 2 big binders of material for a fire science course. NFPA book re fire investigations.
- Policies & Procedures, circa 2007-2008 (Offsite-box 13870)
  Binders: FDNY Building Inspection Safety Program Manual, Chapters 1-6. Binder: Fire Prevention Manual, Chapters 14 & 15 (2007-08).
- Policies & Procedures, circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9082)
  "Uniform Filing System" procedures (1980s), guide to company journal entries (1990s), report writing guide, TIPS Manual (Tactical Information about Perilous Situations), as of 1986. Loose photocopies of clippings, webpages, procedures, tearsheets, etc re a range of things: personnel changes, medical/EMS matters, etc. Seems to be mostly geared to general FDNY press monitoring. Packet of clips from admin notices stapled to summary sheets.
- Policies & Procedures, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9133)
  The entire box is one overstuffed binder of "PA/ID" circulars/bulletins. Unclear what the acronym stands for, but is related to various personnel policies: gifts, ethics, medical leave, residency, probation periods, diversity, workplace harassment, etc. As with many other manuals in the collection, has core documents, with tons of related tearsheets, policies, procedures, stuffed in.
- Policies & Procedures, circa 1990s-2017 (Offsite-box 13873)
  A "binder" labeled "Regulations" which is just a huge pile of tearsheets, memos, procedures, department orders, etc. on administrative and technical FDNY matters. Many of the documents are FDNY issued Regulations, but these are just part of the whole. 1990s-2017.
- Policies & Procedure, circa 1980s-2008 (Offsite-box 13874)
  Binder: ABCs (All Boro Circulars), includes some such circulars, but also "Pass it On Program" notices from the FDNY Bureau of Operations. Binder AUC 138 re: Emergency Command Procedures (including New Years Eve 1999 contingency plans), 1988-90s. Binder AUC 273 re: pilot programs (hoses, rollers, saws, axes, etc.), 1980s-2000s. AUC 210 re: Recordkeeping/reporting, ranges from 1970s-2008ish, with use of NYFIRS.
- Policies & Procedures, circa 1980s-2015 (Offsite-box 13875)
  Binder labeled AUC 250, but has many other All Boro Circulars here: 254 re: chauffeurs, 266 (PCBs), 276 (citywide incident management system (CIMS), 285 re: budgets, 287 re: staffing, and others; inserts of tearsheets, FDNY department orders, copies of "The Chief," etc., circa 2007-15. Binder labeled "AUC 300" includes AUCs beginning with a 3 (e.g., 306 re: children's assistance program, 323, probationary firefighters, 331 re: cellular phone sites, 338 re: water spray/application of water) all with tearsheets, orders, etc. inserted).
- Policies & Procedures, circa 2002-2012 (Offsite-box 13876)
  Binder labelled "AUC 207" re: Subway & Railroad Track Operations, includes various docs on the subject: emergency preparedness exercise 2004, contingency plan for MTA strike 2002, laminated action cards for Penn Station, Overview of the New York Tunnel System 2012, Penn Station and NY Tunnel Familiarization Training 2009, Under River response plan 2006, subway emergency exit locations 2010, tearsheets, memos, etc.
- Policies & Procedures, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13877)
  "Binder" labeled "AUC 1-250" is a thick pile of All Boro Circulars, tearsheets, memos, etc. Includes AUC 159 re: hurricanes and severe storms so has info on Broome County flood 2011 and After Action reports on Irene. Also winter operations, terrorism, and other emergency matters.
- Personal, circa 1970s-1980s (Offsite-box 9762)
  All personal material re Spadafora's schooling. Undergrad years (Queens College, BA, 1977) and graduate years (C.W. Post, MA, 1982). General textbooks (math mostly, some history, dictionary, etc.), school catalogs/bulletins, commencement program/cap for Post and program for Queens, Student Association annual for Queens, some ephemera, many grade reports and other school-related docs specific to Spadafora. A math notebook that looks more to be high school years, and an autograph book (with a few pages with content) for Spadafora's Nativity school (HS? or elementary?)
- Personal, 1941, circa 1960s-1980s (Offsite-box 9763)
  High school diploma (Bishop Laughlin Memorial, 1972) and 4 years of yearbooks, some with grades/docs inserted. Spadafora's father's yearbook (?), 1941 from Jamaica Vocational HS. Elementary school diploma and 3 related photos. John Jay College material: 5 student bulletins/catalogs, blank blue exam books, commencement program. CW Post flyer. 2 social studies texts.
- Personal, circa 1970s-1980s (Offsite-box 9765)
  Spadafora's schoolwork in fire science at CW Post & John Jay: term papers, MA thesis, research notes, reading material, notebooks.
- Personal, circa 1980s-1990s (Offsite-box 9551)
  All related to Spadafora's martial arts training and his work as a sensei. Martial arts belts of various colors. 3 notebooks on moves (1988-92), and other notes/print matter. Notes of receipts for lessons given(?), 1990s. Photo album. 3 copies of sensei Spadafora VHS tape of beginner techniques for goshin ryu jiu-jitsu, and outline for a tape 2. Sensei Spadafora business cards. Patches. Olympic Games pins, mostly judo-related. Magnetic film reel ("Martial Arts Reel") labeled Dub/Master. Martial arts-related snapshots. (Includes artifacts, video)
- Personal, circa 1950s-2008 (Offsite-box 9767)
  Personal material. Several framed photos, mostly from young days. Greeting/Christmas/sympathy, etc cards from 2000s, including prayer card for father (Nicholas, 2003) and mother (Anna, 2008). Certificate of Conspicuous Service awarded to father. Baby/childhood scrapbook for Spadafora (1954+). Unlabeled CD (probably photos?). Varsity letters and related patches. One envelope of photos of firefighting (2006). (Includes digital formats, artifacts)
- Personal, circa 1991-2017 (Offsite-box 9549)
  Many martial arts-related snapshots and larger size photos (circa 1991). File of clippings on Rudy Giuliani and Bernard Kerik conviction (circa 2007-09). File of columns by sports writer Phil Mushnick (NY Post), with Spadafora letter to sports editor (Sound Off) re: support for Mushnick's opinions, 1999. Passports. Misc clippings, tearsheets, notes, cards, some personal, others work-related. Snapshots (travel-related, and other personal). Two matted drawings of dogs. Laminated Fire Officer Vehicle Identification cards. Fire Officers 2017 Workchart Calendar. Rosary beads. Pen with mayor Bloomberg signature. (Includes artifacts)
- Personal, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9550)
  Lots of small memorabilia: Baseball signed by Phil Rizzuto. Mug. Baseball signed by name obscured. Stuffed animal toy. Caps. Keychains. Business cards (Spadafora's and others). Funeral cards for mother Anna (2008) and others. Calculator. Refrigerator magnets. Souvenirs from various places. Pins. Commemorative medallions and coins. Lanyards and IDs. Set of FDNY 9-11-01 memorial series of cards, each card memorializing the firefighters from ladders, etc who died then. Rolodex and other contact papers. CDs of music. FDNY/Spadafora stationery. Patches. Martial arts black belt with "FDNY 9-11-01 Hero" stitched in. (Includes digital formats, artifacts)
- Personal, circa 1960s-2010s (Offsite-box 7284)
  Family film reels; photographs (one framed); artifacts (doorstop, nameplate, palm cross, VP coin); certificates; x-rays of hand. Includes film, artifacts)
- Personal, circa 1977-1990s (Offsite-box 7439)
  Set of files on promotion exams. Some of these are Spadafora's personal files of the exams he took, his answer sheets, and promotion notices, and some other personal career documents. Some of the files include test questions and answers, possibly as preparation. Some admin procedures, eligibility lists, etc. are here in relation to the exams and personal career advancement, circa 1977-early 90s (promoted to Lieutenant in 1986, to Captain in 1989.
- Personal, circa 1970s-2003 (Offsite-box 9784)
  Spadafora's Fire Officers workchart/calendars (1970s-2001); Spadafora's NYC Firefighters Burn Center Foundation calendars for same years; Spadafora's timesheets for maybe the same years. Paystubs for late 1970s-circa 1984. Promotion letters and other letters re Spadafora. Some photos of Spadafora. Some newspapers and articles re: firefighting (maybe involving Spadafora?) and some re Spadafora (at least one letter to editor from him). Metal box with several small address/contact booklets. An unidentifiable artifact. Certificate of Spadafora's completion of Officers Mgmt Institute (2003). (Includes artifacts)
- Personal, circa 2014 (Offsite-box 9845)
  Drafts and related emails re: Spadafora's book "Fire Protection Equipment and Systems" published by Pearson, part of Brady Fire Series, circa 2014. Box only half full.
- Personal, circa 2010s (Offsite-box 9770)
  Bulk relates to Spadafora's final illness. Insurance claims & benefits, general info on hospital and condition. Medications are here. Masks. Many greeting cards sent to Spadafora re his illness. These are mixed with birthday cards, snapshots, and other greetings. Continues in box 9771. (includes artifacts)
- Personal, circa 2010s (Offsite-box 9771)
  All related to final illness. Info, directions, prescriptions, etc. Continued from box 9770.
- Personal, 2010s (Object OS-1)
  Artifacts: 2 boards (48" x 10") reading: "Chief of Fire Prevention, Ronald R. Spadafora", with logos of FDNY and the Bureau of Fire Prevention, perhaps from celebratory event.
- Reference, circa 1964-2005 (Offsite-box 9801)
  Print matter: Bound copies of WNYF in binders: 1964-67; 1970-71; 1972-75; 1989-94; 1996-2000; 1983-85. Loose copies, 2001-05.
- Reference, circa 2000-2007 (Offsite-box 9832)
  Print matter: WNYF, 2000-2007, with extra copies. FDNY Medal Day booklet, 2003-2005, with extras. 2 non-fiction books re fires.
- Reference, circa 2000-2010 (Offsite-box 9738)
  Print matter: WNYF, 2000-2010 (several copies of each. Might not be a complete run, but there are a lot). Also 2 copies of 2007 FDNY annual report.
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9741)
  All print matter: 12 hard cover books related to the history of FDNY, firefighting, and the like. A copy of the "Here is New York" coverslipped catalog.
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9742)
  Mostly print matter: 13 hard & soft cover books re: firefighting (tactics, history, etc.). 3 photocopied articles on same and loose tear sheet. Also 16 issues of WNYF (2006-12). One CD ("Member of L25 drilling with rapid response"). (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 1976-2010s (Offsite-box 9743)
  Print matter. 17 books about fires (Genl Slocum, London), fire depts, firefighters, surviving/preventing fires, etc. 3 commercial VHS re: firefighting. Stack of WNYF (2006-09). 3 issues of Firehouse magazine (1976 (charter issue), 1996, 2001). A few leaflets/pamphlets re firefighting. (Includes video)
- Reference, circa 1969-2010s (Offsite-box 9744)
  Print matter, mostly books, some pamphlets: Histories of FDNY, firefighting standards/practices, firefighting exam prep, books on specific fires, bookseller catalogs for fire books (circa 1969-2001). WNYF issues for 2011-12.
- Reference (Offsite-box 9747)
  Print matter: 10 books, some on general management and others on firefighting.
- Reference (Offsite-box 9780)
  Print matter: tear sheets, textbooks, articles, webpage print-outs, product info. All re: fire suppression: sprinklers, foam, fixed and mobile fire protection systems, etc. Unrelated small file re: Spadafora's travel as assessor to Omaha.
- Reference, circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9835)
  4 thick accordion folders of print matter (tear sheets, manuals, presentations, webpages, etc.), labelled: VI. Water efficiency (reclaimed/reused water, chlorine/chemical use & hazards, water supply systems); VII. Energy & Atmosphere (photovoltaics (PV) & solar thermal); VII. Energy & atmosphere (Refrigeration); IX. IAQ (indoor air quality): SBS/BRI (sick building syndrome/building related illness), Vocs, Bacteria, Mold.
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9836)
  Folders of material that appear to relate to Spadafora's green book. Folders are labeled by chapter and includes print matter and drafts re: green roofs, photovoltaic batteries, daylighting, building ratings, heliostats, construction materials, etc. Print matter includes FDNY specific materials such as strategic plans, as well as web and other print-outs of standards, articles, presentations, reports, product information, etc.
- Reference, circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9005)
  Spadafora Fire Science course exams (2006). Print matter: Fire Protection text by Robert Klinoff (probably course text); occupational safety text, fireground safety text (inscribed to Ron by author), sprinklers/standpipes. "Firehouse" and "Fire Engineering" magazines, 2000s. Various business cards (Not Spadafora). CD re: sprinklers. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 2013-2017 (Offsite-box 9367)
  Folder on Spadafora's article on green batteries/energy storage systems (ESS) for Fire Rescue magazine, 2016; article in WNYF on blue roofs, 2017; high rise fires for Fire & Rescue International; article on EIFS (exterior insulation finishing system) for Fire Engineering, (2015); article on microturbines in WNYF, 2013, and for Fire Engineering. Print matter/reference on dust, modular construction, Vesda smoke detectors. Most of the folders have CDs. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 2010s (Offsite-box 9439)
  Print matter, books re: Fire ventilation practices, forcible entry reference guides, fire operations with elevators, knots, compressed air foam systems, fireground operations, and related loose tearsheets, etc. Folder re: test including list of eligibles for promotion. 2 binders re: Emergency Water supply. Binder labeled "Ladders 1-6" with tearsheets, products, bulletins, etc re: ladders, equipment, dwellings, etc.
- Reference, circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9541)
  Overstuffed binder labeled "Rescue." Mostly tearsheets. Binder re: "Fire Tactics & Procedures," "Emergency response Plan" concerning Hazmat, underground transit, biological.
- Reference, circa 1968-2007 (Offsite-box 9783)
  Manuals: NYC building code and multiple dwelling law, various other NYC reference manuals and guide re: fire prevention (high rises, inspection forms, public assembly (such as concerts). DVD (2005) introduction to new AFID inspection forms and reference book (related paper guides too). Digest of NY state Labor Law, heavily annotated, with course outlines (1968, circa 1982). Building Code Digest also heavily annotated and appears tied to coursework (1970s). "Civilian LPPA" binder of reference material, appears to be related to presentation or coursework. Some child-oriented print matter for recruiting and safety. Presentation "Navigating the NYC Dept of Buildings: Building Information System" (2007). (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9789)
  Material likely related to Spadafora's test prep book. Subjects include: career opportunities, test taking tips, study habits, reading comprehension, lots of math (incl geometry, diagrams, pie charts), resumes/references, fire science basics, and mechanical prnciples. See box 9790 below.
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9790)
  Files of, mostly, webpage print-outs on various topics, likely related to Spadafora's firefighting test prep book, circa 2006. With tearsheets, some publications, Spadafora's drafts, and notes. Subjects include: mechanical principles, math, oral interview tips, reading comprehension, psychological testing, lots on hand tools. See 9790 above.
- Reference, circa 1951-2013 (Offsite-box 9799)
  Binder of WNYFs from 1951-59, with gaps? Binder of WNYFs from 1960-68, probably has gaps. Binder of WNYFs from 1977-79. Binder of WNYF from 1980-82, with related fire tech course and other material inserted. A few WNYFs from 2002-2013.
- Reference, circa 1980-2014 (Offsite-box 9866)
  Print matter: books on chemistry, chemical hazards, emergency response guidebook (2004), fire company apparatus, radiation, "rural firefighting handbook," "Building Construction for the Fire Service" with tearsheets/clips inserted, a few web page print-outs. Binder labeled "Chemical Data Notebook" of tearsheets and clips (and a FDNY Right to Know presentation on toxic chemicals), mostly 1980-90s, with some 2000s. Binder from Keyspan Energy re: "Greenpoint LNG Plant: FDNY Basics." DVD of Williams (brand) Fire & Hazard Control. 2014 Firefighters wall calendar, still shrinkwrapped. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9867)
  Print matter: Thick folders of reading material & student papers re: "bunker gear"/personal protective equipment (PPE)/"Morning Pride" product from courses taught by Spadafora. Folder of material re: Spadafora's article in WNYF re: powdered aerosol suppressant, with floppy and CD-R of photos (with related 2009 WNYF issue). Folders of reference materials on water mist systems, including CDs. Folder of print matter/tearsheets re: wildland firefighting, and binder of training material "Rural Firefighting Handbook." Folder re: thermal imaging camera. Folder and textbook re: smoke control systems. Text re: benefit of behavioral research to fire service. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13862)
  Theme of content is building construction and collapse. Binder with presentation re: high rise building fire/life safety presented by FDNY at CTBUH (tall buildings and urban habitat) conference, 2014, with related material, and some refs to WTC. Binder on Lofts teaching points. Binder on "Construction & Collapse Concerns for the FDNY Officer", 2012, with related textbook by Vincent Dunn. Binder on bowstring building trusses, in relation to firefighter fatalities. Thick binder "Building Construction" of print matter on building construction/collapse (tearsheets, etc).
- Reference, circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 13863)
  2 thick accordion folders re: Lofts: firefighting procedures (drafts & final), print matter, Powerpoints and drafts, etc. on about 50 CDs, visits to other cities, Triangle Fire book, misc related print matter. (Includes digital formats)
- Reference, circa 1986-2014 (Offsite-box 13869)
  Print matter: NYC Fire Code, 2008 with lots of inserts especially study material, and Code for 2014. Report of the NYC, NYS Task Force on Building & Fire Safety, circa 2010. Small binder re: OSHA and combustible dust fires, 2013. Binder of Fire Prevention Information Bulletins, 1986-90s. Thick binder: "Official Compilation of the Rules of the City of New York, Vol 1, Construction & Safety," 1990s, with some inserts.
- Education. Policies & Procedures., circa 1989-2006 (Offsite-box 9849)
  Various binders and booklets for computer training, including Windows, Windows '98 as well as FDNY specific applications such as for Fire Records Management System. Binder "Battalion 4" with procedures, contacts, memos, etc. (1998-2000). Binder of FDNY Publications Unit forms (circa 1997). FDNY Subject Index of Publications (1989 and 1994). FDNY annual reports 1989, 1991. Print matter: Lower East Side photo book, NYC marathon program (2006).
- Education. Policies & Procedures., circa 2000-2008 (Offsite-box 9856)
  7 binders re: fire tech training, labeled numbers: 14, 31, 32, 33, 34, 36, 37. For example, 14 is focused on Spadafora's course in ladders/private dwellings in 2000 for promotion to lieutenant, with overhead projector transparencies and outline. 33 is from his 2007 course on building collapses, etc. Books generally include notes, transparencies, course announcement, and some related reference material. Reference material includes communications manuals, firefighting procedures, AUCs, etc. Overall date range from 2000-08. Floppy disks in some binders. See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Personal. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9831)
  Binder: "plain language writing guidelines" with report writing for FDNY procedure in pocket; also other texts and procedures on writing. Folders and binder of material for first line supervisory training & lieutenant mentoring programs (circa 2006), with floppies. Framed photo of Spadafora with woman connected to Gerry Barbara, who died in service. Spadafora article re: Big Sky Montana volunteer FD (floppy and paper). FDNY approval sheets and related docs for various WNYF articles. Print matter: 100 years on Duane Street battalion history. FDNY Operational Reference book (6th ed, 2005). FDNY Medal Day, 2004. (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Personal. Reference., circa 1977-2008 (Offsite-box 9875)
  Material related to Spadafora's firefighter exam prep book circa 2005-08, including 1) Personal: check stub, contracts, author guide from McGraw-Hill, emails about project, etc. and 2) technical reference material: FDNY probationary firefighters manual chapters and other training bulletins, list of informational resources, NYC's Firefighting training manual (1977), exam prep and info from other cities (e.g., Denver, San Antonio), 1999-2008, Will Chapleau's book on emergency first responders with tearsheets and other inserts, material on memory and visualization. Binder: FDNY Division 6: Lightweight Residential One to Four Family Homes procedures (2000). Accordion folder labeled "Fire Dynamics Simulations" with 33 CDs (many duplicates), including Report of The Station Nightclub Fire (2005), fire at 3146 Cherry Rd in Washington DC (2000), fire in one story restaurant, Texas (2000), two story duplex, Iowa (1999), impact of sprinklers on various materials, other technical subjects, and flashover and other Powerpoints by Chief Galvin (2007). (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9291)
  CD "Surviving the Fireground" training (in connection with safety week). Print matter: Surviving fireground books and other fire safety books; PESH (Public Employee Safety & Health) Violations Training Package; FDNY Safety Command Reviews; FDNY EMS Borough Response Maps (2014). FSETS (Fire Safety Education Tracking System) materials. Binder: User guide for Dispatch system (2010). ARCS (Auxiliary Radio Communications Systems) bulletins & related. VERY overstuffed binder of print matter on "Safety": tearsheets, webpages, emails, closure notices, bulletins, procedures, promotion course prep, "White paper series on the 16 firefighter life safety initiatives." (Includes digital formats)
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 2004-2014 (Offsite-box 9438)
  Print matter: FDNY Operational Reference, 2012, 2014. Lots of loose/in binders print matter re: Firefighting procedures re: dwellings (brownstones, multiples, ventilation, access, wind-driven, tenements, high rises). Folder of "Chief of Department Exam #3539, 2004" material. Binder of tearsheets, manuals, etc re: marine firefighting. 3 issues of "Fire Engineering" magazine.
- Education. Policies & Procedures. Reference., circa 1986-2006 (Offsite-box 9559)